Start. All right. Today's דף daf is ל"א, lamed aleph, but we
pick up at the middle of ל' עמוד ב'. lamed amud bet.
And we are at... no, am I wrong? Am I a דף
daf ahead? I'm sorry.
No, I think you're right.
I'm right, I'm right. I'm right. We pick up in the middle
of ל' עמוד ב', lamed amud bet, or near the bottom,
about 15 lines from the bottom, לא ימכור ברחוק. lo yimkor berachok.
The line starts with the two dots that starts with להני קראי
כסיני. lehani kray kesinnai. Okay, so it's about 15 lines from the
bottom, לא ימכור ברחוק. lo yimkor berachok. So a person should not
sell his fields that are distant in order to redeem his fields
that are nearby. Meaning, even though there's a good reason to do
that, the תורה Torah basically doesn't want... wants you to be holding
on to all of your fields, so it doesn't want... it's understood
it doesn't want you to be making these types of trades. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Mena
hanei milei? Where's this from? Over there. דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, our
rabbis taught, והשיגה ידו. vehisiga yado. It says that he, you know,
his arm... his reach extends, meaning he's able to get the money.
So it's יד עצמו, yad atzmo, that means he himself is able
to get the money. שלא ילווה ויגאל, Shelo yilaveh veyigol, not other
people's money. Okay, so he shouldn't borrow the money in order to
redeem. ומצא, Umatza, and he will... he finds that he has enough
to redeem. פרט למצוי, Prat lematzui,
which excludes when you've already had the money available but you had
it tied up in other things. So if you basically made a
bad decision and you sold your field and you really had the
money available in other things and now you're able to liquidate those
other things to buy it back, it's interesting that here we're saying
that in a way, you know, you should not do that. שלא
ימכור ברחוק ויגאל בקרוב, Shelo yimkor berachok veyigoel bekarov, that you shouldn't
sell distant fields because you already had them available when you sold
your nearby ones. You shouldn't sell them in order to buy back.
ברע ויגאל ביפה, Bera veyigoel beyafeh, in bad and to get with
good. Now, it's a big question what this means. Meaning, it's one
thing to say you shouldn't sell one field to get another because
the goal of the תורה Torah is to have you possess all
of your fields. It's not... what is it... what do they say,
borrowing from Peter to pay Paul? You know, you shouldn't just switch
off. At the end of the day, you'll still have fields of
yours that are sold. So we understand why you would rather have
better fields than worse fields, but in the end, you won't have
all your fields under your control. But if the דרשה drasha is
פרט למצוי, prat lematzui, let's say I... let's say my money wasn't
in fields. Let's say I had my money tied up in stocks
or something like that, and you know, and now I'm able to
liquidate it. Should I not be able to liquidate the stocks that
I had in my portfolio before in order to redeem my field?
I mean, why not? Because it was like a bad decision? I
shouldn't have sold my field in the first place? I mean, that's
one way of understanding it, that the תורה Torah is only sort
of being sympathetic if I had no choice. If I had no
choice, I have absolutely no money,
then it's making it easier for me now to buy it back.
But if I had the money anyway and it was just tied
up, it's not so sympathetic. So I think there's a real question
why is this scenario being excluded. It's being excluded. Now again, בדיעבד
bedieved of course if I went ahead and sold it I could
use the money to buy back my field. No one is preventing
me from once I've done it, but I'm not supposed to sell
these things to buy back my field. So is the reason because
it's just trading one field for another field, or is the reason
because I shouldn't have sold my field in the first place if
I had this money already, you know, if I already had these
assets and I just did not want to liquidate them? So that
is I think a big question because our משנה Mishnah only mentions
the case of one field for another. Okay, so that's the other
thing that's being excluded. And then finally,
כדי גאולתו, kedei geulato, and you have the money in order to
redeem it. כדי גאולה גואל, Kedei geulah goel, only if you have
enough to redeem it. ואינו גואל לחצאין, Ve'eino goel lachatza'in, not if
you only can redeem half. Don't redeem half at a time. It's
either all or nothing. That's not clear why that should be, so
the גמרא Gemara will sort of spell that out a little bit.
But first the גמרא Gemara has a hermeneutic question. Let's take a
look. וממה דמצא השתא משמע? Umemah dematza hashtamashma? It says now you
find the money. ומצא, Umatza, not money you already... not assets you
already had beforehand. So one minute, why do you say the word
ומצא matza means that now you're able to get it together? ורמינהי,
Uremini, I'll ask you a דרשה drasha that we say ומצא matza
means you had it from before. It says ומצא umatza פרט לממציא
עצמו. prat lemamtzi atzmo. So the תורה Torah when it talks about
the person who goes into the forest to chop wood and accidentally
kills somebody, it says that he's chopping with his hatchet there and
the head flies off and it finds somebody and it kills them,
right? And then you know, he goes to the ערי מקלט, arei
miklat, he runs away to be protected from the redeemer of the
blood. So it says that the head flies off ומצא את רעהו,
vematza et re'ehu, it finds his friend. You know, so the גמרא's
Gemara דרשה drasha is it finds his friend, meaning his friend was
already there while this guy was chopping. He was there to be
found. But if the head flew off and after the head flew
off some guy walked into the forest and it struck him and
he wasn't there from beforehand, then he does not have to run
to the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, it's not his fault, he's completely
blameless. So there we said ומצא matza means that the guy was
there already and he just had to find him, as opposed to
when he came later. Here we say ומצא matza means that it
wasn't there beforehand, only now were you able to... collect the funds.
So what does the word מצא matza mean? So there we say
ומצא, u-matza, it finds the friend, פרט לממציא את עצמו, perat le-mamtsi
et atzmo, to exclude a case where the friend makes himself found,
meaning sticks his head out and he wasn't there in the forest
beforehand. ומכאן אמר רבי אליעזר, u-mikan amar Rabbi Eliezer, here from here
Rabbi Eliezer said, אם השליך את האבן מתחת ידו, im hishlich et
ha-even mi-tachat yado, here it gives the case not of the hatchet
head but of a stone. If the,
which I actually think might be the case in the Torah, I
think I might have given the other case. But anyway, it says
if the stone flew out of his hand מתחת ידו, mi-tachat yado,
הוציא הלה את ראשו, hotsi hala et rosho, then after the stone
left his hand this guy stuck his head up, וקיבלה, ve-kiblah, and
it hit him in the head, פטור, patur, you're exempt. אלמא מצא
מידי דאיתא מעיקרא משמע, alma matza midei de-ita me-ikara mashma, מצא matza
sounds like he was already there and the stone just had to
find him as opposed to coming later. So here when it says
I find the funds to pay it, maybe it means I had
the funds, they were just all tied up, you know, and I'm
now able to liquidate them. Maybe מצא matza means it was there
and I only now made it available. So why do we say
מצא matza means it wasn't there to begin with? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר רבא הכא מעניינא דקרא והכא מעניינא דקרא. amar Rava
hacha me-inyana de-kra ve-hacha me-inyana de-kra.
In each case the פסוק pasuk is being interpreted contextually. What does
that mean? הכא דומיא דהשיגה ידו, hacha dumya de-hisiga yado,
the same way it says that now I have achieved the means.
מה השיגה ידו דהשתא, ma hisiga yado de-hashta, the same way השיגה
ידו hisiga yado means now, now it's something like I've now been
able, before I was not השיגה ידו, hisiga yado, before I didn't
have the means, now השיגה ידו, hisiga yado, now I have the
means to buy it back. So therefore if that's what השיגה ידו
hisiga yado means, so מצא matza means now I found the money,
not money that I had available before. So אף מצא נמי דהשתא.
af matza nami de-hashta. והכא דומיא דיער, ve-hacha dumya de-yaar,
and there by the case of the accidental killer it's similar to
the forest. It says you go into a forest. So מה יער
מילתא דאיתא מעיקרא, ma yaar milta de-ita me-ikara, the same way you
go into the forest and all the forest was there. So it
sort of describes a scenario where everything is known and you just
were being a little irresponsible when you were, you know, sort of
chopping your wood. So אף מצא מילתא דאיתא מעיקרא. af matza milta
de-ita me-ikara. So it says when it says it finds the friend,
it means the forest was there, the friend was there, everybody was
there and you knew it and you entered in and you were
being not fully responsible. So but not to, and therefore that's the
context of find means it's all there as opposed to a case
where you didn't know the scenario and the guy stuck out his
head later. So it's interesting that it seems to interpret,
you know, it's a little bit of a question I would say
whether the point is whether it's just like a literary principle or
whether it's also sort of getting to the legal principle. Meaning literarily,
if one scenario is talking about collecting the money, becoming of means,
so מצא matza means that now you became of means. Another scenario
is talking about walking into a forest, so מצא matza means like
also that somehow, you know, just by the literary context you know
that the situation was set. Or is there also an implicit legal
principle here that, you know, in one case since we're saying we
don't want, you know, we only want you to redeem by funds
that you're newly finding,
not borrowed money and not funds that you had before that you
are only now liquidating. And the question again is why? Is it
because on the one hand is it just that like because we
don't want you, you know, borrow from Peter to pay Paul, we
don't want you to, you know, or ראובן Reuven to pay שמעון,
Shimon, we don't want you to, you know, in order to redeem
a field get in debt to somebody else or we don't want
you in order to redeem a field, you know, we don't want
you to have to sell another field. The whole idea is for
you to become whole. So to become whole does not mean trade
one field for another or does not mean be in debt to
another person in order to redeem a field. That's I think the
simple way to explain it. But of course it doesn't explicitly address
the case about what if what I'm liquidating is not a field
but other types of assets. Right? What if I'm just like liquidating
some stock in order to buy back my field? On the one
hand the דרשה drasha is פרט למצוי, perat le-matsui, so that would
be excluded, which is like why? What would be bad? Now at
least I'm getting all my fields back. Okay? And maybe that case
isn't excluded. Maybe it is only selling a field. If that case
is excluded then I think the, then it indicates as I said
before another idea, which is that maybe the תורה Torah is not
being nice to me because it's only being sympathetic because I sold
my שדה אחוזה sedeh achuzah with no choice. But if I actually
did have these stocks available, it just wasn't the right time to
sell it in the market, maybe the תורה Torah is not going
to be so sympathetic to me now that I want to buy
it back with exactly the money that I could have had available
then. earlier. Okay so again the exact exclusion is not so clear
or guidelines I should say. Now ובהקדש U'vehekdesh now that's all about
buying back a field that I sold. But buying back a field
that I sanctified we don't have the same limits. There I'm allowed
to borrow money, I'm allowed to sell another field, I'm allowed to
do it halfway, there there's a lot more latitude to buy back
a field that I sanctified. And now the גמרא Gemara is going
to describe why. מנא הני מילי Mena hani mili where do I
know this from? דתנו רבנן Detanu rabanan we taught: ואם גאל יגאל
Ve'im gaol yigal if a person redeems, this is by הקדש. Hekdesh.
למד Lamed to the double language, thank you, surely redeems, שלווה וגואל
Sheloveh vegoel I can even borrow money to redeem, וגואל לחצאין Vegoel
lachatza'in and I can even do it halfways.
Presumably I could also sell fields that I have but I would
prefer to get this field, although that's not being spelled out. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
it would actually be pretty smart to sell fields because this field
is in הקדש's Hekdesh's hand. If I don't redeem it I'm going
to lose it forever when the יובל Yovel hits. If I sell
a field to buy back the הקדש Hekdesh field, then I win
both ways because I get the הקדש Hekdesh field, I don't lose
it forever, and when יובל Yovel hits, I get back the field
that I sold. So actually there should be no problem in selling
back in doing that. So אמר רבי שמעון מה טעם Amar Rabbi
Shimon mah ta'am why is the תורה Torah giving you more latitude
to buy back a field from הקדש? Hekdesh? לפי שמצינו במוכר שדה
אחוזה שיפה כוחו Lefi shematzinu bemocher sedeh achuzah sheyafeh kocho because by
the selling a field of inheritance you anyway have a serious advantage.
What's your serious advantage? שאם הגיע יובל ולא נגאלה חוזרת לבעלים ביובל
She'im higia yovel velo nig'alah chozeret leva'alim bayovel even if you never
wound up redeeming it, as soon as יובל Yovel hits you'll get
it back. So in that case there's not the same urgency to
redeem it. I mean it's good that you should have your שדה
אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah even now, but worst case scenario you're going to
get it back when the יובל Yovel hits. So therefore הורע כוחו
שאינו לוה וגואל ואינו גואל לחצאין Hura kocho she'eino loveh vegoel ve'eino
goel lachatza'in therefore the תורה Torah is limiting you and saying we're
not going to give you absolute latitude to buy it back. We
don't want to be, you know, don't allow you to buy it
back halfway by borrowing money, you're going to get it back anyway.
אבל מקדיש שדה אחוזה Aval makdish sedeh achuzah but if somebody sanctifies
a field of inheritance, there you really stand to lose it. הואיל
והורע כוחו Ho'il vehura kocho there you have a, you're in a
weak position. שאם הגיע יובל ולא נגאלה יוצאה לכהנים She'im higia yovel
velo nig'alah yotzah lakohanim that if you don't redeem it the כהנים
Kohanim are going to get it and you're going to lose it
completely. So there the, you the תורה Torah wants to give you
a lot of latitude to buy it back because if you don't,
it's going to be completely lost. So יפה כוחו Yafeh kocho the
תורה's Torah's giving you more latitude שלווה וגואל וגואל לחצאין Sheloveh vegoel
vegoel lachatza'in that you can borrow to redeem it and you can
even do it in halves, you don't have to do the whole
thing or nothing.
Okay so that's actually quite fascinating because you know here the גמרא
Gemara is giving like a very persuasive, I mean a very logical
explanation for these differences, but it doesn't always feel it has to,
right? Sometimes it just makes גזירת הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv that's what the
תורה Torah says. But here actually it points out a very nice
logical reason, and you know again it's sort of getting to the
heart of the פסוקים. pesukim. The פסוקים pesukim are trying, are very
concerned about you keeping, retaining your שדה אחוזה, Sedeh Achuzah, which is
why it gets, gets back to you in the יובל, Yovel, which
is why it gives you the right to redeem. But what it's
pointing out is is that you have like a double benefit by
שדה אחוזה, Sedeh Achuzah, you're going to get it back in the
יובל Yovel and you have a right to redeem it against the
guy's will. So at least there's certain limitations on the latter category.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says because either way you'll get
it back. תני חדא Tani chada now we have one ברייתא braita
that says לוה וגואל loveh vegoel you can redeem, borrow to redeem,
וגואל לחצאין vegoel lachatza'in and do it halfways. ותני אידך אינו לוה
וגואל ואינו גואל לחצאין Vetani idach eino loveh vegoel ve'eino goel lachatza'in
you cannot borrow and you cannot do it halfways. Now you could
have said that one is going according to, is one according to
about שדה אחוזה Sedeh Achuzah and the other is about הקדש Hekdesh
like we said, those are exactly the differences. But the גמרא Gemara
understands that they're talking about the same הלכה halacha and that it's
a מחלוקת. machlokes. So who are the different opinions? לא קשיא Lo
kashya it's not difficult. הא רבנן הא רבי שמעון. Ha rabanan ha
Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if you remember was the one
that said this logic about מה טעם. mah ta'am. Since you have
more ability in one case, so you don't have as much latitude.
The other case you're, you stand to lose, you have more latitude.
So that whole idea is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So presumably this
is talking here about not our משנה, mishna, this is talking about
the case of let's say the what do you call it, the
when you're מקדיש makdish a field. So there רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says oh you're מקדיש makdish you stand to lose it, you have
a lot more latitude. And the other is the רבנן, Rabanan, we've
never explicitly seen a רבנן Rabanan that argues, but implicitly the position
that argues and says no, you have to apply the same הלכה,
halacha, the same הלכה halacha that applies to to redeeming a field
you sold applies to sanctifying a field. The same way you have
limits by redeeming a field you sold, you have limits by sanctifying.
So that's how רש"י Rashi reads this. According to this then there
actually is a debate how much latitude you have by sanctifying a
field. תוספות Tosafot doesn't say that. תוספות Tosafot says no no no.
The two cases we said we had פסוקים, pesukim, ואם גאל יגאל
ve'im gaol yigal was a פסוק pasuk by sanctifying, everybody agrees. Everybody
agrees that by buying, by buying it back when you sold it
you have a limited right, by buying it back when you sanctified
it you have more extensive right, those are the פסוקים. pesukim. The
question is what about a case the תורה Torah and this is
fascinating because it says something about like what what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon gained by explicating the logic. What he gained by explicating the
logic was the ability to apply it to a case the תורה
Torah isn't addressing explicitly. Because there's three cases you can buy something
back: a field that you sold, a field that you sanctified, and
we're about to get to this in the next משנה mishna Anybody
know from בהר? Behar? What's the third case you can buy something
back?
בתי ערי חומה,
Batei arei chomah, a house that you sold in a walled city
you have a year to buy it back. And if you don't
you lose it completely. So there, what's the story? Can I borrow,
can I do it halfway? What do I have the latitude or
not? The תורה Torah doesn't say. So here, תוספות Tosafot very beautifully
says, ah, so according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that tried to
infer the logic of the תורה Torah that it's giving me more
latitude when I stand to lose, so then he would say that
I have that same latitude by בתי ערי חומה. Batei arei chomah.
Because if I don't buy it back in the year I'm going
to lose it completely. Whereas the Rabbis that aren't bothering to explicate
any logic, they just do like a גזירת הכתוב, gezerat hakatuv, so
therefore as the תורה Torah isn't explicit, it'll go by the rules
that I don't have the latitude and therefore the Rabbis will say
that no I'm sorry I don't have that type of latitude by
בתי ערי חומה Batei arei chomah I can't borrow I can't do
it halfway. So that's very nice because A, it just works with
the earlier גמרא Gemara they agree on these and here's the third
category they disagree on, but it's also nice because it tells you
the importance of trying to say it's not a גזירת הכתוב, gezerat
hakatuv, but here's the logic. Because once I identify the logic, it
can tell me how to apply it in cases that I don't
know what the תורה Torah says. Okay. What?
You're saying it's a principle, give a principle, defining it for...
Right,
you identify the legal logic behind it. Okay, and now so talking
about בתי ערי חומה, Batei arei chomah, now we're בתי ערי חומה.
Batei arei chomah. So the end of ערכין Arachin as you see
is working first it does the end of, it's basically a lot
of the שמיטה Shemitah stuff. It's interesting, if you ask somebody where
do you think the laws of buying back fields and sanctifying fields
during the יובל Yovel and בתי ערי חומה Batei arei chomah is,
they'd probably guess it's in מסכת שביעית. Masechet Shevi'it. But מסכת שביעית
Masechet Shevi'it devotes itself to the more agricultural aspects, and here really
it's in the end of ערכין. Arachin. So we did the stuff
at the end of בחוקותי, Bechukotai, we did the sanctifying of the
fields, now we're in בהר, Behar, we did the selling of the
fields, and now in the selling of בתי ערי חומה, Batei arei
chomah, where the תורה Torah says that you have a year to
buy it back and if you don't, this house is in a
walled city, it goes completely over to the person, you've lost it
completely even when the יובל Yovel hits. המוכר בית בבתי ערי חומה,
Hamocher bayit bevatei arei chomah, if somebody sells a house in a
walled city, הרי זה גואל מיד, harei zeh goel miyad, you can
redeem it right away. וגואל כל שנים עשר חודש, vegoel kol shenem
asar chodesh, you have a month, excuse me, a year, 12 months
to redeem it. הרי זה כמין ריבית ואינו ריבית, harei zeh kemin
ribit veino ribit, it's like ריבית ribit but not real. Meaning, remember
before we had the discussion about, you know, after two years you
buy it back proportional and so on, and one of the hanging
questions, unresolved questions we had is like if you just do a
fixed computation based on years, then it's not always so fair. Maybe
he's made some capital improvements, maybe he harvested more than the actual
number of years, okay. But it was like a fixed formula the
תורה Torah said. Well here also you have a fixed formula. I
sell you a house for, I don't know, a million dollars, okay,
I have a year to buy it back. Let's say six months
later I buy it back. How much do I buy it back
for? So here the תורה Torah does not say you do some
proportional computation. So the assumption is I buy it back for the
purchase price. So I give you the same million dollars back. So
what happens? You basically gave me a million dollars, got back your
million dollars, and you got to live in the house for six
months. So you basically benefited from effectively lending me the money because
you got back what you paid and you got six months use
out of the house. So that's like ריבית, ribit, you gave the
money, you got it back, and you got the use of those
period months in between. So it's like ריבית ואינו ריבית, ribit veino
ribit, it's not really ריבית. ribit. Why is it not really ריבית?
ribit? Because it wasn't a loan, it was a purchase and then
a repurchase option. What? And you don't have to redeem. And you
don't have to redeem. So both of those things, excellent, both of
those things are what the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about.
One is that it didn't have to end that way, legally I
could have left it in your hands. So that's called צד אחד
בריבית, tzad echad beribit, meaning only one way would have led to
this problem. The other option in this deal would have allowed you
to, you just would have kept it. The other reason is that
it's not a, it's not framed as a loan, it's framed as
a purchase. So it's a purchase with a repurchase with the end
result of it, you got more out of the deal than I
did. Okay, so there are two reasons why it's not ריבית, ribit,
we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, מה המוכר mah
hamocher now, מת המוכר יגאל בנו. met hamocher yigal beno.
Let's say the seller dies, his son is still allowed to redeem
for him. The question I have is whether it's only limited to
the son, which the גמרא Gemara does not really explicate because well
first of all there's a question about other heirs who are not
the son, but even beyond that there's a question that when the
תורה Torah talks about selling your field, it says, you know, אחד
מאחיו יגאלנו, echad meachav yigalenu, או דודו או בן דודו יגאלנו, o
dodo o ben dodo yigalenu, right, any one of the relatives can
come redeem the field for me. What about the bayit in בתי
ערי חומה? Batei arei chomah? Is the same true? Point that anybody
can, anybody help me out and redeem it for me? Does it
have to be, you know, does it have to be me? I
guess the, so that's again not clear, here it speaks about the
son. מת
הלוקח יגאל מיד בנו. met halokeach yigal miyad beno. If the purchaser
died, you're not limited to buying it back from the purchaser, you
can buy it back from his son. Now, אין מונין שנה אלא
משעה שמכר. ein monin shanah ela mishaah shemachar. You count the year
not based on a calendar year, but based on a year from
the day it was sold, שנאמר עד מלאת לו שנה, sheneemar ad
melot lo shanah, until a year is full. So a full year
means from the day it was sold, a full, you know, well
not 365 days, 354 days, whatever, a full lunar year. Now we're
actually going to talk about that, about the, you know, about the,
sort
of. What does that word coming to include? להביא את חודש העיבור,
lehavi et chodesh ha'ibur,
that if it were a leap year and there were thirteen months,
that's still you still get the so it you still get the
full thirteen months because a full year, the fullness of the year
means even if it's the larger year, it's got thirteen months, you
get back to the same calendar date that you sold it. So
you sold it on, I don't know, ז' ניסן, Zayin Nisan, so
you have up until ו' ניסן Vav Nisan to buy it back,
and only when ז' ניסן Zayin Nisan hits, then does it go
over, even if that meant thirteen months because it was a leap
year. Okay, that's the first opinion. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, Rebbi has
a very unusual opinion. ליתן לו שנה ועיבורה, liten lo shana ve'iburah,
not a שנה מעוברת, shana me'uberet,
but the year and its. That sounds like the same, but the
Gemara's going to show that according to Rebbi, what that actually means
is a solar year. Fascinating. When it says שנה תמימה, shana tmima,
it means not in a special case that you had a leap
year, it means that if you had to choose what how to
define a year, you define the year that is the fuller year.
Which year is the fuller year? The solar year is the fuller
year, not the lunar year, because it's longer and because it's in
a way it's more accurate as the full year in terms of
the, you know, Earth getting back to its original position. So Rebbi
says that the Torah actually means you have a solar year to
buy it back.
Quite fascinating, right? Because we only know about the importance of a
solar year to be a corrective for the lunar year, but to
actually give weight to the solar year directly in Halacha is very
strange. הגיע יום שנים עשר חודש ולא נגאל, higia yom shneim asar
chodesh velo nigal, let's say the day actually arrived, which presumably means
the same calendar day you sold it, like the seventh of Nisan,
or according to Rebbi, I don't know, April 12th, whatever the date
was in the lunar solar calendar, and it wasn't redeemed, right? You
realize that that basically is going by the, you know, it means
according to him you look at the secular calendar. Anyway, what would
you do?
חלוטה לו, chaluta lo, then it's totally sold over to the guy
and it cannot and it cannot be bought back.
אחד הלוקח ואחד הניתן לו במתנה, echad halokeach ve'echad hanitan lo bematana,
whether it was purchased or whether it was given as a gift,
if you didn't do it within the twelve months, the guy gets
it and you've lost it from your control, שנאמר לצמיתות, shene'emar litzmitut,
for perpetuity. Now, I looked around yesterday because of this case of
אחד הניתן לו במתנה, echad hanitan lo bematana, the Gemara's going to
base it on a pasuk that even מתנה matana is included in
מכר, mecher, but here's what I don't understand. If you give it
to somebody as a gift and you want to redeem it within
the twelve months, what do you redeem it for? How much do
you have to redeem it for? Right? Can you just say, "Oh,
I want it back because you didn't pay anything"? Do you have
to redeem it for market value? I mean, this goes to show
how much these laws are not really lived because, you know, the
Rambam just quotes the Gemara. There's even the ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan
wrote a sefer, the ערוך השולחן העתיד, Aruch HaShulchan HeAtid, where he
tried to take all the halachot of זרעים Zeraim and קדשים Kodashim
and pasken them as if, you know, they were real halacha. He
doesn't discuss it. I couldn't find anybody that discusses it. How much
do you buy it back for? Presumably the market value, but I
really don't know. Alright, anyway, let's take a look now at the
Gemara.
I have to say also, I've never given enough thought, and I
didn't in preparation for today's daf, I'll see if I can find
something for tomorrow, about why this פשט הפסוק, pshat hapasuk, like why
the Torah, you know, totally reverses it. Like, you know, there's why
I mean, I guess the concept of שדה אחוזה sde achuza is,
you know, in an agricultural society, people can live in different places,
and especially if you're living in a עיר חומה, ir choma, it's
a like it's a city, it's not rural. So the sense of,
like, you know, ancestral land, inherited land, is more the homes that
you own out in the fields, you know, out in the country.
Homes that you own in a city by nature are more transitory.
So I can understand that the laws of going back in the
יובל Yovel and so on don't apply in sort of city homes.
But what I don't understand is why there's this idea of, you
know, a year right to buy it back, unless somehow the point
is is that, you know, maybe the Torah is just being sensitive.
Sometimes you're in a monetary crunch and it's still a tragic thing
to leave your home, so it's giving you this latitude at least
there. But there are two questions. One is why does it not
have the halacha about חוזרת ביובל, chozeret baYovel, which again can make
sense if we think about the emphasis on the agricultural reality. But
why also the right to buy it back in a year is
a separate question. Yes.
And the right to buy it back is just an entitlement to
buy it back at the sale price. Right.
Or to no, but also to force the guy to buy it
back. Ah. No, that's the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that
the guy could could say I don't want to and you can
force him to give it back to you. So that's really, yes.
It's gone for good. Yeah. If he takes the ownership for the
house. Right. He has to give it back.
Within the first year. Not give it back. He has to be
able to sell it back. It's like you wrote in the contract
that you have the right to reverse reverse the sale within the
first year.
Oh, you'd have to put it in the contract.
No, I said it's like you did. The Torah you don't have
to. The Torah says a sale of a home in a walled
city can be reversed within the first year. It is the seller's
right to reverse it anytime he wants within the first year. Oh,
okay. Yeah. What? No, after the first year... That's it. The guy
owns it. End of story.
Right, because of the יובל? Yovel?
Nothing. Guy keeps it. The יובל Yovel does not return the houses
of בתי ערי חומה Batei Arei Chomah because I said that makes
sense because you know the whole emphasis here of the sense of
the land that really matters, the land that's the ancestral land in
an agricultural society is the farmland and is the home out there.
This is just city dwellers and they're basically transitory anyway or something
of that nature. It doesn't have that same sense of ancestral land.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מתניתין דלא כרבי. Matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi. Our משנה Mishnah is not like
רבי. Rabbi. דתניא, Detanya, I mean there's a רבי Rabbi later in
the משנה Mishnah but the first point is not, because we turn
in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, ימים. Yamim. It says,
it says
ימים תהיה גאולתו, Yamim tihyeh geulato, his redemption will be in, you
know, in days. What does that mean? So אין ימים פחות משנים.
Ein yamim pachot mishnayim. It means two days, which means that according
to רבי, Rabbi, it's not that גואל מיד. goel miyad. גואל מיד
Goel miyad literally means that the day you sold it you can
reverse it on the same day. So according to רבי, Rabbi, the
guy gets to keep it at least for two days. You have
to wait. Not exactly מיד, miyad, only after two days. All right,
ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, ה-ימים מאי עבדי ליה? ha-yamim mai avdi leh? What do
they do with that word? מיבעי ליה מיום ליום, Mibaei leh miyom
l'yom, to tell you that it means a full year, so that
until the same day that you sold it, only when the same
day arose does it go over to the guy. ורבי, V'Rabbi, מיום
ליום מנא ליה? miyom l'yom m'na leh? How does he know that?
נפקא ליה מעד תום שנת ממכרו, Nafka leh m'ad tom shnat mimkaro,
until the year of sale is complete, which means a full year
till the day you sold it. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, the Rabbis, ההוא מיבעי
ליה שנת ממכרו שלו ולא שנת של מנין עולם. Hahu mibaei leh
shnat mimkaro shelo v'lo shnat shel minyan olam. So basically, which is
a way of saying that you're right, actually, the idea of a
full year is from שנת ממכרו, shnat mimkaro, to tell you that
it goes by the year of the sale, not the calendar year,
שנת ממכרו. shnat mimkaro. So it's interesting, the משנה Mishnah learned it
out from עד מלאת לו, ad melot lo, the ברייתא, Baraita, the
גמרא Gemara is at least saying it's from שנת ממכרו, shnat mimkaro,
the year of the sale, you measure a year from the date
of the sale, not from the calendar. So back to the question,
what do you do with the word ימים? yamim? וימים מיבעי להו
למעת לעת, V'yamim mibaei lehu l'me'et l'et, from, from the exact moment
to the exact moment. What does this mean? דאי מעד תום שנת
ממכרו, D'ee m'ad tom shnat mimkaro, it was just from the year
of the sale, הוה אמינא מיום ליום אין מעת לעת לא. hava
amina miyom l'yom in me'et l'et lo. It goes to the day
but not to the hour. So meaning, if I sold it to
this guy on, you know, ז' סיון Zayin Sivan at 12:00, 12:00
PM, he can buy it back until, excuse me, I can buy
it back until 11:59 ז' סיון Zayin Sivan the next day, right?
We don't say, no, I sold it ז' סיון Zayin Sivan I
can only buy it back till ז' סיון Zayin Sivan the next
year. No, I can buy it back till a minute before the
exact moment that I sold it, till 11:59 on ז' סיון Zayin
Sivan the next year. כתב רחמנא ימים, Katav Rachmana yamim, so therefore
ימים yamim is coming to, extra word ימים yamim is to tell
me that I have an exact year measured not only in days
but in minutes. ורבי, V'Rabbi, מעת לעת מנא ליה? me'et l'et m'na
leh? Where does he know this principle? Assuming that everybody agrees to
it, which wasn't even mentioned in the משנה. Mishnah. נפקא ליה מתמימה.
Nafka leh mitmimah. It says full, so full year means again measured
to the very minute, not just to the day. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, the
Rabbis, ההוא מיבעי ליה לעיבורה, Hahu mibaei leh l'ibura, that תמימה tmimah
is coming to tell you that even if it's a leap year
you get the extra month. ורבי נמי ההוא מיבעי ליה לעיבורה, V'Rabbi
nami hahu mibaei leh l'ibura, doesn't רבי Rabbi need it for that?
Although רבי Rabbi reads it differently to tell you solely you're not
losing your year. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי, hachi nami,
so he does need it, so where does he get the idea
of the exact
minutes? So מיום ליום מעת לעת מעד תום שנת ממכרו נפקא. miyom
l'yom me'et l'et m'ad tom shnat mimkaro nafka. He gets when it
says when the year is done, so the year means the full
year, whether to, not only to the very day but to the
very minute. So that's the גמרא Gemara just working out the different
דרשות, drashot, but in the end we've learned something quite fascinating. We've
learned number one that according to רבי Rabbi there's a two-day wait,
which what good does two days do, but okay. And the other
thing is, is that the year is measured not just what the
משנה Mishnah said, to the day, but it's measured to the minute.
And this raises fascinating halakhic questions about is this the exception or
is this the rule? And you could imagine questions, right? Somebody's on
his בר מצווה Bar Mitzvah day, okay? Let's say somebody was born
on, I don't know, same case, ז' סיון. Zayin Sivan. So when
does he become 13? Right, his 12 years end on ו' סיון.
Vav Sivan. He enters his 13th year right on ז' סיון. Zayin
Sivan. So on that day, can he, let's say his בר מצווה
Bar Mitzvah is ממש mamash the same day he was born, ז'
סיון, Zayin Sivan, but he happened to be born at 6:00 PM.
בר מצווה, Bar Mitzvah, the קריאת התורה kriat haTorah or whatever is
taking place at 11:00 AM. So right, only if you measure by
days he's in his 13th year, right? If you measure by minutes
or what, he's not in his 13th year. Do you go by
days or do you go by minutes? Right, there's questions also we
learn about בכורות, bechorot, you know, there as well, 30th, 31st day,
do you go by minutes, do you go by days? How do
you count these things? So if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot basically has both opinions. He doesn't know which way
to go. מיום ליום מעת לעת עד תום שנת ממכרו. Miyom l'yom
me'et l'et ad tom shnat mimkaro. So תוספות Tosafot says here במסכת
נדה פירש הרב רבינו חננאל דדוקא, b'masechet Niddah peirash haRav Rabbeinu Chananel
d'davka, which is one of the בעלי התוספות, Ba'alei haTosafot, דדוקא בבית
ערי חומה בעינן מעת לעת d'davka b'bayit arei chomah beinan me'et l'et
לשעות, l'sha'ot, so we only measure by minutes or he says hours,
whatever, only by this. This is the exception. אבל אינך דהתם, Aval
inach d'hatam, all those other cases, and that's where it lists all
these things about being בר מצווה, Bar Mitzvah, בת מצווה, Bat Mitzvah,
all these other cases where where you measure by based on a
year from the time, you know, a year, not a calendar year,
but a year from an event, דמצי למימר דאזלינן בתר שנים שלהם
ולא בתר שנים dematzi lemeimar de'azlinan basar shanim shelahem velo basar shanim
שלנו ובכולו לא בעינן מעת לעת. shelanu u'vechulu lo be'inan me'es le'es.
All other cases, all other cases you don't need it, דבבית אריכא
דוקא הוא דגלי קרא. de'be'bayis areicha davka hu de'gali kra. This is
the exception. אבל אינך לא. Aval inach lo. What? There's a lot,
there's a whole perek
biblical in their...
There's a lot, a girl that's more than three years old, I
mean, there's a lot of הלכות halachos based on particularly ages of
people.
Well, a lot of those, those ages are now stand-ins for שתי
שערות.
shtei
se'aros.
No, no, they're not stand-ins. The גמרא Gemara understands that
י"ג שנה י"ב שנה yud gimmel shana yud bais shana is הלכה
למשה מסיני, halacha le'Moshe mi'Sinai, it does not treat it as a
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. We have a חזקה chazakah which is we assume that
if somebody is בר בת מצוה Bar Bat Mitzvah that they have
also the סימנים, simanim, but הלכתית halachically you need both and the
assumption is that the years are הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha le'Moshe mi'Sinai,
not just a way of approximating. Then the גמרא Gemara
says, ובתופס כתבו, ve'Tosfos kasvu, so that's רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, I
don't know who, תוספות Tosfos is one of the other בעלי התוספות,
Ba'alei Tosfos, כאן הוא הדין בכולהו דבעינן מעת לעת ושעות kan hu
hadin be'chulhu de'be'inan me'es le'es ve'sha'os that really it's this is the
rule, not the exception, that you always measure, okay? Which actually, you
know, comes up, people have their בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah celebration, you
know, or you could have a similar, you know, ברית, bris, no,
ברית bris nobody says, it's a good point, but ברית bris nobody
says. But anyway, but this is a real question, do you need
it to be till the minute, you measure by the minute or
by the days? General assumption is by all these things we measure
it by the days, not by the minute, but it's interesting to
see that תוספות Tosfos has that question, whether this is the rule
or this is the exception. Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara.
ברית Bris is phrased differently, right, ביום השמיני, bayom
hashmini,
on the eighth day, right, exactly, exactly. Okay, שנותיו כר... shenosav ke...
okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara, הרי זה כמין ריבית. harei zeh
kemin ribbis. So now we're going to get a very little foray
into ריבית, ribbis, thankfully very little, we will have more of it
in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, so you stick with us for about
another four months, four years. Okay, but here it's very, very light.
הרי זה כמין ריבית. Harei zeh kemin ribbis. ותניא הרי זה ריבית
גמורה. Ve'tanya harei zeh ribbis gemura. We have a ברייתא, braisa, we
have a ברייתא braisa that says
it's not just like ריבית, ribbis, it is ריבית, ribbis, אלא שהתורה
התירה זו, ela she'haTorah hitira zu, but the תורה Torah allowed it
in this case, but it really is ריבית. ribbis. So what's the
debate about? אמר רבי יוחנן לא קשיא הא רבי יהודה והא רבנן.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan lo kashya ha Rabbi Yehuda ve'ha rabbanan. It's a
debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן rabbanan whether a
case like this normally would be ריבית ribbis or not. דתניא, De'tanya,
where's that debate? We taught in the ברייתא. braisa. הרי שהיה נושה
בחבירו מנה, Harei she'haya nosheh be'chaveiro maneh, so basically I owe somebody
a hundred dollars. ועשה לו שדהו מכר. Ve'asah lo sadehu mecher. Now,
I could give my field as collateral, and then there's all these
major discussions in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, if my field is collateral
for the loan, can he be reaping the benefits of the field
while it's he's holding onto it as collateral? There you can understand
a real ריבית ribbis concern, right? Because there it's collateral, it's all
in the loan context. What if it's not exactly framed as related
to the loan? Here's what we do. I owed, you know, I
owe James there a hundred dollars, and what I say to James
is, James, I'll sell you my field for a hundred dollars. Not
collateral for the loan. I'll sell it to you for a hundred
dollars. But there's a little condition. The condition is, is that if
I am get together a hundred dollars within the next three years,
you know, or whatever the duration of the loan is, and I'm
able to give you a hundred dollars, I'll have a right to
buy it back. So it's sort of like our case, meaning it's
different that it starts with a loan, but it does move into
the מכר mecher realm, because the way I pay my loan back
to James is I sell him my field, but I retain a
right to buy to buy it back within a certain period of
time. If I do buy it back within that period of time,
so then I paid James off for his loan, but he has
now lived in it for the last two, three years, okay? But
lived in it not as a loan, lived in it as a
purchase that I had the right to repurchase. Okay.
How is it different from collateral?
Because collateral, the whole thing is framed as a loan. If you're
sitting in my house and my house is collateral, you are in
my house because you're holding onto it because of the loan and
you're reaping benefit now in the context of the loan. Okay, if
I sold you the house, so now you're there because we have
a sale. The fact that I was motivated to do the sale
because I owed you
money, it's not a loan at all. What? With the right to
retract.
Yeah, exactly. But the point is it was in the context, it
was motivated, obviously the loan is in the background. But the immediate
way the sale, the transaction was framed was as a sale. Okay,
so it makes it maybe a little more kosher.
It's more like a somewhat contract, you're not owning your stuff with
contract. I understand.
But you're selling, exactly, exactly, that's what makes it a little bit
more kosher. Okay, so there's a מכר mecher component and there's also
the fact that it didn't have to end that way, that in
the end you might be able to keep it. So that's called
the צד אחד. tzad echad. So those are the two components here.
And he eats the fruits.
Right, and James does get the פירות peiros during that period. That's
the... yeah, so let's take a look. הרי שהיה נושה בחבירו מנה.
Harei she'haya nosheh be'chaveiro maneh. I owe James a hundred dollars. ועשה
לו שדהו מכר. Ve'asah lo sadehu mecher. I said I'll sell you
my field. בזמן שמוכר אוכל פירות, Bizman she'mocher ochel peiros,
if I'm getting the fruits for the whole time, מותר, mutar, obviously
that's okay, what's the big deal? לוקח אוכל פירות, Lokeach ochel peiros,
if however James is eating the fruits, אסור. assur. That's forbidden. Rebbe
Yehuda because he's benefiting from it and I might I might wind
up buying it
back. רבי יהודה אומר אף בזמן שלוקח אוכל פירות מותר, Rebbe Yehuda
omer af bizman shelokeach ochel peiros mutar, even that's okay. אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rebbe Yehuda, said רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, מעשה בבייתוס בן
זונין. maiseh be-Baitos ben Zonin. This guy בייתוס בן זונין Baitos ben
Zonin came up a lot in the גמרא, Gemara, I mean in
the משניות. Mishnayot. He obviously was some type of a businessman, he
had a lot of, he dealt with a lot of things. Anyway,
very often he is, people sort of refer to cases that involved
him. So this person, what?
Negatively or positively?
No, neither, just as evidence for the הלכה. halacha. There's a story
about, yeah, there's a story about that he had a whole מצה
matzah baking factory, that he was, I'm serious, that he would use,
not exactly, that he had like, he had like cookie cutters. And
the question was, the גמרא Gemara says that you're not allowed to
make shapes in your מצה matzah because it'll take too long and
it'll lead to חמץ. chametz. It says, whoa, what if you use
like בייתוס'ס Baitos's cookie cutters? So it doesn't take any time. So,
you know, so anyway, there's always, there's a lot of stories about
בייתוס. Baitos. Anyway, so he said there was a story with him
שעשה שדהו מכר על פי רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. she-asah sadehu mechar
al pi Rebbe Elazar ben Azarya. He did this thing, he made
his field, you know, he sold it based on the advice, the
direct hit of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rebbe Elazar ben Azarya, ולוקח
אוכל פירות היה, ve-lokeach ochel peiros hayah, and the purchaser ate the
fruit even though he had a right to buy it back. So
אמרו לו, amru lo, the rabbis said back to him, you got
the facts mixed up. משם ראיה? Misham rayah? You want to bring
a proof from that? מוכר אוכל פירות היה, mochaier ochel peiros hayah,
ולא לוקח. velo lokeach. You've got the facts mixed up. The seller
was the one that ate the fruit, not the purchaser. Okay? So,
you know, you always have to know what the facts are. Anyway,
fine. So now we see that they are debating this case where
I sold you something, I have a right to buy it back.
If I buy it back, you will have benefited from it without
any, you know, without any
payment on your side. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What are they
really debating? Or meaning, how would you conceptualize their debate? צד אחד
בריבית איכא בינייהו. tzad echad beribbit ika beinaihu. They're debating if only
one way has to lead to something problematic. If I buy it
back, then we have the problematic thing that this guy benefited, you
know, and in the end, right, you know, he paid me the
money, he got back the money he paid me, and he benefited
from it in the interim. But it doesn't have to end that
way. If I don't buy it back within the contractual period, he
keeps it. So is that something which doesn't have to end in
this guy benefiting incorrectly, is that defined as ריבית? ribbit? Even if
in the end he does benefit for nothing, but it didn't have
to end that way, so it's not considered a ריבית ribbit transaction.
So צד אחד בריבית איכא בינייהו. tzad echad beribbit ika beinaihu. תנא
קמא סבר צד אחד בריבית אסור. Tanna Kamma savar tzad echad beribbit
assur.
The first תנא tanna holds yeah, that's a problem because if in
the end it ends that way, then he's got something for nothing
for laying out the money and getting it back. רבי יהודה סבר
צד אחד בריבית מותר. Rebbe Yehuda savar tzad echad beribbit mutar. No,
that's not a problem. Since it didn't have to end that way,
even if it does, it's not defined as a ריבית ribbit transaction.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, דכולי עלמא צד אחד בריבית
אסור. dechulei alma tzad echad beribbit assur.
Everybody would say that is a problem. If that were the only
aspect to it, it is a problem. So what's the debate about?
והכא בריבית על
מנת להחזיר איכא בינייהו. vehacha beribbit al menat lehachazir ika beinaihu. Here
it's a special case. Here again, this was not spelled out, but
the point is like this. Let's say James basically is in the
field and he's got, benefiting, and then I exercise my right and
I buy it back. But let's say what we've also stipulated is,
if I exercise my right, then you'll pay me for the usage
of it. Okay? That wasn't spelled out. Will that now kosher the
whole thing up? Okay? So in the interim, he is benefiting from
it, but in the end, you know, he'll give the money back
anyway. So there logically it makes a lot of sense. Since right
now he's not benefiting from it as ריבית, ribbit, he's benefiting from
it as a sale, right? So then you would think, and if
it turns out to be that it did revert, he'll pay me
for it. So, you know, like it makes sense that it should
be totally okay. So והכא בריבית על מנת להחזיר איכא בינייהו. vehacha
beribbit al menat lehachazir ika beinaihu. מר סבר אסור ומר סבר מותר.
mar savar assur umar savar mutar. So what's the position of the
one that said forbidden? I guess the position is that in the
interim, at the moment that this sale reversed and it basically has
turned in from a sale to a loan because I bought it
back, you know, it didn't really become a loan, but effectively it
became a loan because it reverted. So yes, James will give the
money back, but he still has now benefited from something that in
the end of the day wasn't a sale. And until he's given
it me back, there was incorrect benefit. So anyway, this is how
the גמרא Gemara frames it.
And it sounds like the whole thing was like תנאי tnai and
that's impacting למפרע? lemafrea? Right, basically.
Okay, but basically what is not explicitly explored and רש"י Rashi brings
in is because רש"י Rashi says, well wait a minute, in our
משנה Mishnah it wasn't על מנת להחזיר, al menat lehachazir, right? In
our משנה Mishnah the guy doesn't pay for the usage and there
was a similar debate. One said it's okay, one said it's not
okay. So רש"י Rashi says our case in the משנה Mishnah is
better. Our case in the משנה Mishnah was not preceded by a
loan. Our case in the משנה Mishnah was a straight thing, a
sale with a right to buy it back. But therefore that also
makes it more kosher and therefore even if the money isn't given
back, there's a possibility that it's not real ריבית. ribbit. Okay? Because
the whole thing was framed fundamentally as a
sale. All right, so that's the issues here, whether it was real
ריבית ribbit or whether it was, and the תורה Torah allowed it
or whether it wasn't real ריבית, ribbit, both because it didn't have
to end that way and because it was fundamentally framed as a
sale. Now, מת מוכר יגאל בנו. meis mochaier yiga'el beno. the son
can redeem it. פשיטא *pshita*, obviously. מהו דתימא *mahu detaima*, ואיש כי
ימכור בית bayis מושב *ve'ish ki yimkor beis moshav*, אמרה רחמנא *amra
Rachmana*, if a man sells and that he shall redeem it, אמרה
רחמנא *amra Rachmana*, והאי לאו מכר mecher. *vehai lav mecher*, and this
guy is or should be מוכר *mocher*, והאי לאו מכר mecher, *vehai
lav machar*, and this guy didn't sell it, קא משמע לן *kamashma
lan*, וישג גאולתו *veyasag geulato*, its redemption shall be for the year,
so since it sort of disguised describes the redemption as a, you
know, as a noun by itself, not just as the act of
this person doing it, it means that we're trying to achieve the
redemption in a broader range of cases. מכל מקום *mikol makom*, even
if it's not the seller, even if it's only his son. מת
הלוקח יגאל מיד בנו *meis alokeiach yigoail miyad bno*, if the purchaser
dies, you can redeem from the son. פשיטא *pshita*, of course, why
not? No, same point. מהו דתימא *mahu detaima*, לקונה אותו lakoneh oso,
*lakoneh oso*, it speaks about the purchaser, so maybe it has to
be that particular actor that you are redeeming from. So אמרה רחמנא
*amra Rachmana*, והאי לא קנא *vehai lo kanan*, this guy, the son,
did not buy it. קא משמע לן *kamashma lan*, וישג גאולתו *veyasag
geulato*, מכל מקום *mikol makom*, its redemption shall be, so meaning that
we want to achieve redemption, so we are not limited to the
seller or the buyer, and therefore even if it gets passed down,
one of them dies, the son can take over. מכל מקום *mikol
makom*, again, what's interesting is what if it's not either of them,
right? What if it's, what if after the guy, well the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to talk about that scenario, right? What if
after the guy bought it, he sells it to somebody else? Right?
Can you redeem it from somebody that's a complete, you know, third
party? What if a relative, can a relative redeem it from him
if it's not my son? Okay, so that's not yet fully spelled
out. רב שימי בר אשי *Rav Shimi bar Ashi*. אין מונין לו
אלא משעה שמכר *ein monin lo ela mishaa shemachar*. Okay, you can
only, you go from the year from the date of sale, as
we said, this is even measured to the minute, although that might
be the exception, but it's not a calendar year. תנו רבנן tanu
rabanan, *tanu rabbanan*, שנה *shana*, it says a year. איני יודע אם
שנה לראשון אם שנה לשני *eini yodeia im shana larishon im shana
lashaini*. I don't know if it's talking about the first or the
second guy. And here we bring in the scenario that there are,
that there are two purchasers. I sell it there to James. James
does a quick flip, makes a profit, sells it to Mordechai. Okay.
Is my year go by, there's two questions. Do I measure the
year by when I sold it to James or when James sold
it to Mordechai? And of course, the next question is what? What's
the purchase price that I have to buy it back for? Right?
Based on James, based on Mordechai? So that's the question we're now
going to deal with. Okay. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan, *tanu rabbanan*, שנה
*shana*, a year. איני יודע אם שנה לראשון אם שנה לשני *eini
yodeia im shana larishon im shana lashaini*. Do I measure it from
my sale to James or when James sold it to Mordechai? כשהוא
אומר עד מלאת לו שנה תמימה tmima. *keshehu omer ad melos lo
shana temima*, until a full year is filled for him, him meaning
the seller, הוי שנה לראשון *havei shana larishon*. Okay, the first guy,
because it's focused on my year from the moment I sold it.
All right. Now, למי חלוט *lemi cholat*? Before without discussing yes, the
redemption price, here's another question. The year is over. Who gets to
keep it? Okay, now. Okay, I didn't buy it back. Who gets
it permanently? Now, of course, it makes sense that Mordechai gets it
permanently, he's the one who's holding onto it. What would it mean
for James to get it permanent? What it would mean for James
to get it permanent is if it effectively transferred over to James
and then Mordechai, James, James would have a year from his sale
to redeem it from Mordechai. Okay, that's the possibility. Meaning, right, you
got it? I sold it to James, six months later he sold
it to Mordechai. If I don't redeem it, is James now considered
the original owner of that field vis-a-vis his sale to Mordechai and
he has a year from his sale to Mordechai? What? Okay. Yeah.
So that's the question. Or do we just say since I didn't
redeem it, it goes fully over to the person permanently over to
the person who's currently in possession of it? And Mordechai now gets
it for the full year, gets it
permanently.
There is no permanent, there is no right to buy back unless
you yourself have held possession for the full year, for a full
year. What?
No, no, no. Are you saying the first way? The first way
is that nobody gets it permanently unless a year goes by?
No, you offered that either James would have it or
James doesn't get it away from you. But the point is that
James is now considered to be the permanent owner and he has
still the remainder of the year to buy back.
No, I'm arguing the different from that because I'm saying that James
wouldn't get the right now as a result of that six months,
six months, so no one would currently be considered to be the
permanent owner. Oh, no, no, no.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, no, no, no. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
considering that possibility. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is considering that after the
year, either James is the permanent owner and he has six months
to buy back from you, or you're the permanent owner. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that at the end of the year, some
transfer occurred, okay, of permanent title. And the question is whether it's
to James or was it to you? Let's take, let's take a
look. למי חלוט *lemi cholat*? Who gets it permanently? רבי Rebbi, אליעזר
אומר לראשון חלוט *Rabbi Eliezer omer larishon cholat*. James, he's the one
I sold it to. So if the year goes up, he gets
permanent title. Okay, which means that he still has, you know, X
number of months to buy it back from the second guy. רבי
Rebbi יוחנן אומר לשני חלוט *Rabbi Yochanan omer lashaini cholat*. No, the
second guy gets permanent title. Once it leaves my possession, it goes
permanently over to the one who currently has it. You can sort
of imagine like the whole, you know, like a whole industry of
speculation based on this. This is like options and then you buy
options and futures and those things. Anyway, fine. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, בשלמא לרבי אליעזר, Bishlama l'Rebbe Eliezer, makes sense
according to Rabbi Eliezer that James gets it, but לדידי כמאן מנינן
l'didi kamaninan since the year's measured from my sale to James, so
therefore when the year's up, James gets the permanent title. אלא רבי
יוחנן מאי טעמא? Ella Rebbe Yochanan mai ta'ama? Why does Rebbe Yochanan
say we measure the year from my sale but the but it
goes over to the person currently in possession? So אמר רבי אבא
בר ממל מה מכר לו ראשון לשני כל זכות שתבא לידו. amar
Rabbi Abba bar Memel ma machar lo rishon lishani kol zchus shetavo
l'yado. Very famous phrase that the גמרא uses in multiple places, which
is what the first guy sold to the second guy all of
his rights, which means that when James sold it to Mordechai, he
basically Mordechai basically now is the ממלא מקום, memale makom, is the
substitute for James. So halachically he takes over any rights that James
had. So since James had the right to become permanent owner at
the end of the calendar of the year from my sale, when
that year ends, that right has already been transferred to Mordechai. So
Mordechai owns it not by virtue of him being sitting on it,
but by virtue of him having purchased all of James's rights. He
now represents James. Okay, so that's why the argument that Mordechai gets
it now fully. אמר רבי אבא בר ממל. Amar Rabbi Abba bar
Memel. Now, now, okay, so that would have been more interesting to
continue to explore also the question about do you go by the
first purchase price or the second purchase price, presumably the first, since
everything now is being done via James. So presumably if I'm redeeming
it from Mordechai, I am redeeming it based on the first purchase
price, right? That's presumably. But anyway the גמרא doesn't explore that. Now
it gets to a fun discussion about the calendar issues and about
leap years and אדר ראשון Adar Rishon and אדר שני. Adar Sheni.
So since we're moving into אדר, Adar, it's a little bit relevant,
let's take a look. אמר רבי אבא בר ממל מכר שני בתי
ערי חומה. Amar Rabbi Abba bar Memel machar shnei batei arei chomah.
I sold two houses in a walled city. אחד בחמשה עשר באדר
ראשון, Echad b'chamishah asar b'Adar Rishon, one on the 15th of
אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, on פורים Purim nonetheless, although פורים Purim was
only אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, okay, but it's בתי ערי חומה, batei
arei chomah, so it would be פורים Purim for a walled city,
the 15th
anyway. Okay, ואחד באדר שני, v'echad b'Adar Sheni, and one on ראש
חודש אדר שני. Rosh Chodesh Adar Sheni. Now what happens? Next year
rolls around and there's only one אדר. Adar. So the when אדר
Adar one hits, the second sale has had its full year, the
later sale has had its full year because it's אדר Adar one.
The first sale, the earlier one, only has its full year two
weeks later when it's אדר Adar 15. Right? It's the reverse. It's
not you started by a normal אדר Adar and then you have
a leap year and it's extended. You started by a leap year
and then, so the guy that was sold in אדר ראשון Adar
Rishon is going to have, you know, more time. So,
כיון שהגיע יום אחד באדר של שנה הבאה, keivan shehigia yom echad
b'Adar shel shanah haba'ah, when the first day of אדר Adar came
in the second year, עלתה לו שנה. alsa lo shanah.
So then the year is full for the guy that you sold
it to second. זה שמכר לו בחמשה עשר של אדר ראשון, Zeh
shemachar lo b'chamishah asar shel Adar Rishon, however the guy that you
sold it to on the 15th of the first אדר, Adar, the
earlier
sale, לא עלתה לו שנה עד חמשה עשר באדר של שנה הבאה,
lo alsa lo shanah ad chamishah asar b'Adar shel shanah haba'ah, until
the 15th of the next אדר. Adar. Okay, so the irony is
of course that the guy you sold it to earlier, his year
isn't over till later. So מתקיף לה רבינא, mas'kif lah Ravina, so
רבינא Ravina said, I mean this is the obvious point that he
was רבי אבא בר ממל Rabbi Abba bar Memel was making, but
רבינא Ravina surfaced the irony or the לימא ליה, l'eima leh, why
can't he say, now of course the purchaser wants the year to
end earlier, right? Because if the year ends earlier, he gets the
house permanently. So he by telling him, oh your year isn't over
for another 15 days, he actually that's a bad thing for him,
it means more time for the guy to buy it back. So
why doesn't he say, the guy who bought it on the 15th
of אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, אנא קדים שכינא נורא מקמי דידך? ana
kadim shachinu ra mikmi didach? He says, look, I lit the fire
before you. It's a funny little example, but it means, you know,
I started living in my house two weeks before you, why is
your year over sooner than mine? I want my year to be
over sooner. So the גמרא says, משום דאמר ליה את מחית לעיבורא,
mishum d'amar leh at machis l'iburah, you said, what do you want?
You got it during an עיבור ibur year. Those are the concepts,
this is a funny exchange, meaning on the one hand it's saying
it's not fair, you know, it's not logical, and saying, yeah, okay,
but in a formal speaking in a formalistic way, your year goes
by the calendar date and it doesn't go by number of days,
right? I mean this by the way is different for רבי, Rebbi
רבי goes by number of days, he goes by a solar year.
But when you go by a lunar year it has these peculiarities
and that's what the הלכה halacha is. Now we give another case
about a similar about a full year but having nothing to do
with our בתי ערי חומה. batei arei chomah. ואמר רבי אבא בר
ממל, V'amar Rabbi Abba bar Memel, said רבי אבא בר ממל, Rabbi
Abba bar Memel, נולדו לו שני טלאים. noldu lo shnei t'la'im. You
had two lambs that were born in your
flock. אחד בחמשה עשר של אדר ראשון ואחד באדר שני. Echad b'chamishah
asar shel Adar Rishon v'echad b'Adar Sheni. One on the 15th of
אדר ראשון Adar Rishon and the other on the first of אדר
שני. Adar Sheni. Now why does a year matter for a sheep
born in the flock? So רש"י Rashi says it's about the בכור.
bechor. The מצוה mitzvah is to bring a בכור bechor within the
first year, שנה בשנה לפני ה' אלהיך. shanah b'shanah lifnei Hashem Elokecha.
It's not פסול pasul after the year but the מצוה mitzvah is
to bring it within the first
year. ורבינו גרשום V'Rabbeinu Gershom says, this is what I had thought,
is that the הלכה halacha of the question about, you know, a
lot of times in the תורה Torah it says certain קרבנות korbanot
are only kosher if the animal is within its first year, right?
Certain animals, if it's a שה, seh, if it's an איל, ayil,
is it considered a lamb, is it a ram? And that depends
on its birthday. Is it within the first year, between the first
and the second year and so on. So how do you measure
that? You measure that by the calendar date, even though the calendar
date is not always the same number of days based on the
leap year. Okay, so זה שנולד באדר שני, ze she'nolad b'adar sheni,
the one that was born in the second אדר Adar in ראש
חודש, Rosh Chodesh, כיוון שיהיה יום אחד באדר של שנה הבאה, keivan
she'yihiye yom echad b'adar shel shana haba'ah, when it's the ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh of next year's אדר, Adar, עלתה לו שנה, alta lo
shana, his year is up because it's the first day of אדר.
Adar. זה שנולד בחמישה עשר באדר ראשון, ze she'nolad b'chamisha asar b'adar
rishon, and the guy who was born earlier on the fifteenth of
the first אדר, Adar, his birthday, he doesn't get to have his
birthday, לא עלתה לו שנה עד חמישה עשר באדר של שנה הבאה.
lo alta lo shana ad chamisha asar b'adar shel shana haba'ah. He
doesn't get to have his birthday until the fifteenth of the next
one. Now is that good, is that bad? You know, the point
is here it's not exactly the same as בתי ערי חומה, batei
arei choma, but whatever, if it means let's say a בכור, bechor,
it means עשר תעשר, aser t'aser, good, you have more time. But
anyway, so מתיב לה רבינא, metiv lah Ravina, so רבינא Ravina asks,
ולימא ליה, v'leima lei, why doesn't one lamb say to the other
one, אנא קדים אכלי ירוקא מקמי דידך, ana kadim achli yeroka mikamei
didach, I've been eating vegetables before you, meaning I was grazing in
the field for two weeks, so how come you get your birthday
before me? Okay, so the גמרא says, משום דאמר ליה את נחית
עיבורא ואנא לא נחית עיבורא, mishum d'amar lei at nachit ibura v'ana
lo nachit ibura, because you were born in the עיבור ibur year
and I wasn't born in the עיבור ibur year. Fine, it's just
such a funny exchange, meaning one is saying it's not fair and
the other's saying tough luck, you know, that's the date you were
born. But you know, it reminds me of all those stories they
do on the news right about, you know, when somebody's born on
February 29th, you know, so it says, you know, he's only had
his, he's forty years old, he's only had his tenth birthday or
something. Okay, tough luck. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא says, הא תו
למה לי היינו הך, ha tu lama li hainu hach, why did
you need this case of the lambs? It's basically the same point.
מהו דתימא התם דכתיב תמימה, mahu d'teima hatam d'chtiv tmima, by the
בתי ערי חומה batei arei choma it says a full year. So
a full year means that, that we would go by, I don't
know why it would mean that, you know, anyway, somehow it means
we would go by the exact date. הכא דלא כתיב תמימה, hacha
d'lo ktiv tmima, when it's the case of lambs, whether it's talking
about the בכור, bechor, whether it's talking about when is it considered
to be a ram, it doesn't say תמימה. So הכא דלא כתיב
תמימה לא, hacha d'lo ktiv tmima lo, so maybe I would say
you don't go by this, you go, I don't know, by the
number of months. Because if you think about it, the one that
was born on the fifteenth of אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, right, it
actually is more than a full year, right? Because if it's born
on the fifteenth of אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, its real twelve months
is the fifteenth of שבט Shevat in the next year, right? He
says שבט. Shevat. No, not even, what's the month before אדר? Adar?
שבט. Shevat. So it's the fifteenth of שבט. Shevat. Okay, so maybe
if it said a perfect year, so we can't, so that, you
know, that might mean that, you know, somehow you have to do
the same date. But if it didn't say perfect, it just said
a year, then you would actually measure the duration, and the duration
would have been over in שבט. Shevat. קא משמע לן דשנה שנה
מהדדי גמרי, ka mashma lan d'shana shana me'hadadi gamri, we make a
גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. Okay, so on the one hand, you go,
don't go by the calendar ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but on the
other hand, you do go by the calendrical date. And it has
to be the same calendrical date, even if that leads to this
weird variance, like if you were a normal year leading into a
leap year, it's thirteen months, leap year leading into a normal year,
you could get these ironies. So it does go by the day
you were born, not by, but it does, but it goes by
the calendrical date and also by the time and the hour. Let's
keep on going. I think we're actually going to catch up today.
Okay, now I just gave a small הערה. he'ara. Okay, let's keep
on going. כשהוא אומר תמימה רבי אומר ליתן שנת עיבורא. keshehu omer
tmima Rebbi omer litein shnat ibura. רבי says you actually go by
the solar year, you look at essentially the secular
date. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, שנת תמימה, shnat tmima, a full year,
רבי אומר מונה שס"ה ימים כמנין ימות החמה, Rebbi omer mone sh'sa
yamim k'minyan yemot hachama, 365 days. So by the way, it's not
exactly looking at the solar calendar because if it were like a
February 29th or whatever, there's a correction there. He was not saying
you, but, you know, so he's not saying you, I mean it's,
you don't go by like June 12th, you go by 365 days.
You know, three out of four years it's going to be the
same, you know, solar calendar date, but he doesn't actually say you
look at that date, but you do count an exact solar year,
365 days. וחכמים אומרים מונה שנים עשר חודש מיום ליום ואם נתעברה
נתעברה לו. v'Chachamim omrim mone shneim asar chodesh miyom l'yom v'im nitabra
nitabra lo. You count twelve months, if it's a leap year then
you get an extra month, so גזונטהייט. gezuntheit. All right, הגיע יום
שנים עשר חודש ולא נגאל, higia yom shneim asar chodesh v'lo nigal,
twelve months come and it's not redeemed, it goes over to the
guy completely. תנו רבנן, לצמיתות, l'tzmitut, for perpetuity, לחלוטין, l'chalutin, end of
the story, absolutely, cannot be reversed. דבר אחר לצמיתות לרבות את המתנה,
davar acher l'tzmitut l'rabot et hamatana, even a gift. מאי טעמא, mai
ta'ama, where do you get that? The Torah is talking about sale.
סמיך לצמיתות, samich l'tzmitut, it could have said צמית, tzmit, which would
have meant, and לצמיתות l'tzmitut is an even stronger emphasis, which means
that there are other cases where this works as well. Now of
course it's a little funny because if I would not have put
gift in here, what would I have said? I would have said
that like anything else, a sale is final and, and you can't,
you know, of course it's for perpetuity. By putting gift in the
פרשה, parsha, it actually undermines the לצמיתות. l'tzmitut. It gives me a
year to buy it back, right? So meaning we're learning it from
לצמיתות, l'tzmitut, but the effect of putting gift in this discussion is
not to say that it transfers, a gift transfers over more fully,
that I would have said under a normal case, any sale is
permanent, right? By putting gift in this discussion, it gives me the
right to buy it back. Is that clear? No? If,
if we would have
said... If I would have given you a gift of land, would
that would you have owned it for perpetuity? Yes, right? Okay. So
by putting it by putting things that this פרשה parsha of buying
back בתי ערי חומה Batei Arei Choma includes the case of gift,
what does it do? It actually it lifts me to it gives
me the right to buy it back, right? Unless the opposite point
is that had it not been there I would have said that
if I would have given a gift then I would have gotten
it back at the יובל. Yovel. And that actually we're going to
see an interesting debate. Do you get gifts of land back in
the יובל? Yovel? Okay. So you wouldn't buy it
back, you'd take it back.
Well, that's my question. If gift had not been in this פרשה,
parsha, what would I have said with a gift? Would I have
said it's permanent and I can't buy it back? Okay, then putting
it into this פרשה parsha just gives me a right to buy
it back. Well, that's the question. We don't know how you would
buy it back, maybe it goes by market value. That's never spelled
out. I mentioned that before. Okay, but by putting in this פרשה
parsha does it give me the right to buy it back or
by putting in this פרשה parsha does it say when the יובל
Yovel comes I don't get it back? Okay, what would I have
said anyway by a gift of a בית in בתי ערי חומה
Batei Arei Choma regarding the יובל? Yovel? So maybe maybe if that
I would have thought I would have got it back, by putting
in this פרשה parsha it means I lose it and that's the
emphasis of לצמיתות, litzmisus, that it's totally lost to me even if
it's a gift. Okay. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? צמית צמיתות Tzamitz tzamitzus
because of the עיקרא דצמית ikra d'tzamis and it said צמיתות. tzamitzus.
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב פפא. Amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Pappa. The rabbis
said in front of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. כמאן דלא כרבי מאיר.
Keman d'lo k'Rabbi Meir. This is not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
דאי רבי מאיר, D'ee Rabbi Meir, כרבי מאיר האמר מתנה אינה כמכר.
k'Rabbi Meir ha'amar matana eina k'mecher. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
a gift does not go back in the יובל, Yovel, it's not
like a מכר. And therefore he normally does assume that the word
that when the תורה Torah talks about sale it's limited to sale.
So here too if the תורה's Torah talking about sale it's limited
to sale, gifts are not included. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
אפילו תימא רבי מאיר. afilu teima Rabbi Meir. No, it can be
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. שאני הכא דרבי רחמנא לצמיתות. Shani hacha d'rabi
rachmana litzmisus. Here the תורה Torah is including לצמיתות, litzmisus, so it's
a broader category. So even if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
gifts don't go back in the יובל, Yovel, here it would a
gift is included in sale. אמרו רבנן לרב פפא, Amru rabanan l'Rav
Pappa, the rabbis said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, ואמרי לה רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, v'amri lah Rav Huna brei d'Rav
Yehoshua l'Rav Pappa, והא גבי יובל דכתיב תשובו v'ha gabei Yovel d'chsiv
tashuvu לרבות את המתנה. l'rabos es hamatana. You can't say that no
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree when you have an extra word
in the פסוק. pasuk. Because you have an extra word in the
פסוק pasuk by יובל Yovel as well. It says every person shall
go back to their field, תשובו, tashuvu, and that extra is assumed
to be extra and from there we learn out לרבות את המתנה
l'rabos es hamatana that you get back the field you gave as
a gift. ורבי מאיר לא קאמר. V'Rabbi Meir lo ka'amar. And רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't include it. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I
don't care that it says תשובו, tashuvu, the תורה Torah only talks
about sales and not gifts. אלא הא ודאי דלא כרבי מאיר. Ella
ha vadai d'lo k'Rabbi Meir. You're right, רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir not
impressed by the extra word of the פסוק. pasuk. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says only sales not gifts. So here actually it is it
does again, what's not clear is is that according to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, let me frame the question this way, according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that does not include gifts, what's the story if
you give as a gift a house in ערי חומה? Arei Choma?
Does it go back in the יובל Yovel or not? Right? If
it's not included in the פרשה, parsha, do on the one hand
you don't have a right to buy it back. On the other
hand does it go back to you in the יובל? Yovel? I
don't know, maybe it does. Anyways that's not clear. But we say
that it's a gift is like a מכר, you can buy it
back, if you don't buy it back it goes to the it
goes back you've lost it completely. Okay, let's finish up to the
משנה. mishna. תנו רבנן, המקדיש בית בבתי ערי חומה הרי זה גואל.
hamakdish bayis b'Batei Arei Choma harei zeh goel. So if you sanctify
a house in בתי ערי חומה Batei Arei Choma you can redeem,
remember like if you sanctify your field you can redeem, וגואל לעולם,
v'goel l'olam, you can redeem it until the יובל Yovel hits, sanctifying
a field. גואלו אחר מיד הקדש, Goalo acher miyad hekdesh,
let's say somebody else purchased it from הקדש. hekdesh. What happens if
I sanctify a field and somebody purchases it? He keeps it till
the יובל, Yovel, comes the יובל Yovel it goes to the כהנים.
kohanim. Let's say it's a house in ערי חומה. Arei Choma. I
sell it and David here buys it off of הקדש. hekdesh. I
sanctify it, David buys it off of הקדש. hekdesh. Then we go
by the year rule. הגיע יום שנים עשר חודש, Higia yom shneim
asar chodesh, since he did an act of purchase effectively, he purchased
it from הקדש, hekdesh, if 12 months come ולא נגאל v'lo nigal
and I didn't redeem it from David, now once David gets it
from הקדש hekdesh I should be working to get it back from
David. If I didn't after 12 months, היה חלוט לו, haya chalut
lo, then he keeps it. So when he buys it from הקדש
hekdesh it's like he bought it from me and I have the
12 months to buy it back and if not he gets it
completely. מנאני מילי? Minani mili? Where do you know this from? אמר
שמואל דאמר קרא, Amar Shmuel d'amar kra, the verse says, לקונה אותו,
it goes to the one who purchased it, ואפילו מיד הקדש, v'afilu
miyad hekdesh, even if he gets it from הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so
that's important. I sanctify, David buys, it's like he bought it from
me, the year starts ticking.
Now, גמרא says, ולחלטיה הקדש, v'lichletei hekdesh, why doesn't הקדש hekdesh get
it after a year? After I sanctified it, if I waited a
year after sanctifying it, let it go straight to הקדש, hekdesh, let
הקדש hekdesh be as good as having sold it to somebody. So
אמר קרא, amar kra, לדורותיו. l'dorosav. It goes for all generations. יצא
הקדש שאין לו דורות. Yatza hekdesh she'ein lo doros. הקדש hekdesh doesn't
have generations. As רש"י Rashi says, there is no procreation by הקדש.
hekdesh. So
so therefore the idea of generations is irrelevant. So that's actually interesting,
here הקדש hekdesh is in a weaker position than a normal person
and even after a year I can always redeem it from הקדש.
hekdesh. Okay, now לא יצא lo yatza now שאין דורות. she'ein doros.
לא יצא ביובל, lo yeitzei bayovel, לא יצא ביובל, lo yeitzei bayovel,
the תורה Torah says, right? When now it's gone back to the
פסוק *pasuk*. The תורה *Torah* says, right, when, now it's going back
to the פסוק *pasuk*. The תורה *Torah*, if I sell it and
it goes fully over to the other person, it does not go
back to me in the יובל *yovel*. This is quoting the פסוק
*pasuk*. למה לי *lamah li*, what is that including? What is that
coming to tell me? אמר ספרא לא נצרכה אלא למוכר בית בבתי
ערי חומה ופגע בו יובל בתוך שנתו *amar Safra lo nitzrecha ela
lemocher bayit bebatei arei chomah upaga bo yovel betoch shenato*. Let's say
I sold it to David, this house in the walled city, six
months before the יובל *yovel*. So it's not yet permanently transferred over
to David. It hasn't been a year. Maybe in that case I
get it back? סלקא דעתך אמינא ליפוק ביובל קא משמע לן לא
יצא ביובל *salka daatach amina leipok beyovel ka mashma lan lo yeitzei
biyovel*. No, houses in walled cities are completely out of the category,
and even if the יובל *yovel* hits within the year. What has
not been explained is if I sanctify a field to הקדש *hekdesh*,
right, what happens and at no point David buys it, nobody buys
it, what happens at the end of the year? At the end
of יובל *yovel*, I mean, what happens by יובל *yovel*? Right, is
it that it goes back to me, is it that it goes
to כהנים *kohanim*, or what's suggested here is that יובל *yovel* is
basically irrelevant to houses in walled cities. So it would seem like
if I sanctify it and it's sitting in the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash*'s control and יובל *yovel* hits, it seems like nothing happens, right?
It just stays there, either I buy it back or somebody else
buys it and then the year starts ticking. But again, it's also
similar to the question I asked according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
that doesn't include מתנה *matanah*. So if I give somebody a מתנה
*matanah* in a house in a walled city, what happens at the
יובל *yovel*? Is יובל *yovel* completely irrelevant to houses in the walled
city? You know, and there's a couple of implications to that. All
right, so to be continued.